Finding Aid for International Neighbors Records, 1958-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
International Neighbors records 1958-2013
International Neighbors.
85229 Bk 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, women's organization formed to provide friendship and assistance to foreign women visitors to Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan. Minutes, reports, bulletins and newsletters, slide presentations, and other materials relating to their activities.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from International Neighbors (donor no. 6081 ) in multiple accessions.
The record group is open to research.
International Neighbors is an independent organization of women in Ann Arbor, Michigan that extends friendship and assistance to women from other countries during their temporary residence in Ann Arbor. In 1958, Esther Dunham approached Kathleen Mead, then Administrative Assistant of the University of Michigan's International Center, for ideas about helping foreign wives of faculty and students of the University of Michigan. Between 1958 and 1960, they coordinated informal, monthly gatherings of neighborhood groups for tea and English conversation. In 1960, as the participation in neighborhood groups expanded, the organization formally adopted by-laws and elected an executive board. Immediate goals were to create a loan center for baby equipment and household items, introduce new foreign wives to the organization, mobilize more Ann Arbor hostesses, and provide booklets about living in Ann Arbor. In 1963, International Neighbors was incorporated as a non-profit charitable organization.
From its beginning in 1958, the organization has provided activities and services to meet the needs of foreign women, particularly those who are wives and mothers concerned with housekeeping and family life. There are two classifications of participants: Participant-Guests and Participant-Hostesses. Any woman may volunteer to be a hostess. Guests include the wives, mothers, or sisters of foreign students, visiting faculty, staff, researchers, or visiting scholars of the university, or other foreigners not affiliated with the university.
Neighborhood Tea Groups are the main activities of the organization. Guests meet in a hostess's home monthly for conversation, refreshment, and companionship. Participation has included more than four hundred hostesses and six hundred guests. International Day is a monthly morning program for hostesses and guests in which various nationalities are given the opportunity to share cultures and learn about American life. The organization also has continued to provide English Conversation Groups for women who wish to learn and improve their English with the assistance of a volunteer teacher. Discussion groups are offered for fluent English-speakers around various topics of interest, such as about books or cooking. International Neighbors also coordinates an exchange for women who need to borrow household items, such as cooking utensils or sewing machines. There is also a special services division that helps women with prenatal care, enrollment of children in school, provision of winter clothing, and other difficult needs.
The records of the International Neighbors document the activities, services, and organization of the International Neighbors. It is significant for showing the development of a community organization to satisfy needs of foreign women in Ann Arbor and for revealing social interactions among American and foreign women. The record group is organized into three series: Administrative Files, Activities, and Publications.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); International cooperation.; International Neighbors.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Chapels.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Parks.; Chapels--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Concordia College (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ice hockey.; Ice skating.; International Neighbors.; Parks--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Winter.; Women.; Women--Organizations.
Contributors:
Dunham, Esther.; Mead, Kathleen.
Genre Terms:
Slides (photography)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series includes records of the foundation, organizational structure, and operation of the International Neighbors. The Annual Meeting Reports and Minutes provides a year-by-year summary of the major activities and concerns of the organization. Two folders of histories include Esther Dunham's account of the organization's beginnings as well as later chronologies and summaries. The Participant-Guests Committee folder is a rich source of statistical information about the number and nationality of the organization's participants. The folder of Presidential Annual Reports fills in the gaps of documentation in the 1990s, when Board Minutes and Treasurer's Annual reports are missing.
  - Annual Meeting Reports and Minutes 1959-1999, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Articles of Association, By-laws, and Policies (Box 1)
  - Board Minutes 1961-1992, 1995-1999, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1978-1997 (Box 1)
  - Fran Miller Special Projects Fund 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - History, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation application 1963-2004 (Box 1)
  - Job Descriptions (Box 1)
  - Kopelman Concern 1970 (Box 1)
  - Mailings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Officers and Executive Board 1960-1998 (Box 1)
  - Participant-Guests Committee 1960-1997 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Participant-Hostesses Committee (Box 1)
  - President's Annual Report 1991-1999 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Annual Report 1961-1990, 1993-1999 (Box 1)
- Activities
  The Activities series contains organizational records and announcements of International Neighbor's main activities, such as the annual Fall Reception or the monthly Neighborhood Tea Groups. Documentation is best for the 1960s and 1970s, but scattered for later decades. The series also includes slide programs produced for 1974-1975. The slides contain pictures of guests, hostesses, and members of the executive board participating in multiple activities, such as International Days. They also include pictures of recommended recreational activities in Ann Arbor.
  - Discussion Groups 1960-1975 (Box 1)
  - English Conversation Groups 1960-1981 (Box 1)
  - Fall Reception 1958-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Family Picnic 1960-1966 (Box 2)
  - International Days 1960-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - International Neighbors Exchange 1962-1979 (Box 2)
  - Neighborhood Tea Groups 1959-1984 (Box 2)
  - Slide Shows
    - Out and About in Ann Arbor 1975 (Box 2)
    - The Story of an International Neighbor 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Slides, 33mm, color (Box 2)
  - Special Services (Box 2)
  - Studies
    - Bibliographies 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Chinese Participation 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Summer Tea 1967-1990 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Anniversary 1977-1978 (Box 2)
- Publications
  The Publication series contains publications the International Neighbors produced for helping foreign women adjust to life in Ann Arbor, for introducing the organization to new foreign women, and for reporting their activities. Bulletins offer monthly summaries of activities, but are scattered for the 1990s. The Handbook for Hostesses provides detailed instructions for the format of Neighborhood Tea Groups and for interacting with women of different cultures. The Living in Ann Arbor series offers a basic orientation to the community and government. Brochures encourage new participants and provide succinct summaries of the organization's purpose.
  - Brochures 1960-1998 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins 1961-1999 (scattered), 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Newsletter (scattered) 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - Handbook for Hostesses 1974, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Living in Ann Arbor 1963-1997, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Later accession records
  - Tributes to Special Members, Newspaper articles and Memorial Tributes (Box 2)
  - Extra historical materials 1960-2013 (Box 2)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 2)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - 2007-2008 (Box 3)
  - 2008-2009 (Box 3)
  - 2009-2010 (Box 3)
  - 2010-2011 (Box 3)
  - 2011-2012 (Box 3)
  - 2012-2013 (Box 3)